<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A profession of faith comprizing the ancient forms of the Catholick Church with other articles relating to the terms of communion with the present church of Rome / by E.S., an English Catholick.</title>
            <author>E. S., English Catholick.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13750</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13587183</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13587183</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100585</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61439)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100585)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 851:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A profession of faith comprizing the ancient forms of the Catholick Church with other articles relating to the terms of communion with the present church of Rome / by E.S., an English Catholick.</title>
                  <author>E. S., English Catholick.</author>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ascribed by Wing to Edward Stephens (Socrates Christianus), an anti-Catholic writer.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Creeds.</term>
               <term>Creeds --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100585:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100585:1"/>
            <p>A Profeſſion of FAITH COMPRIZING The Ancient FORMS OF THE CATHOLICK CHURCH, With other Articles relating to <hi>The Terms of Communion</hi> WITH THE Preſent Church of ROME.</p>
            <p>By <hi>E. S.</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:100585:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100585:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>SINCE <hi>our Saviour</hi> hath ſo affectionately expreſſed and ſo admirably demonſtrated his <hi>Love to his Church,</hi> and hath ſo effectually recommended and injoined to all his Diſciples, the Members of it, Mutual Charity one to another: and his Bleſſed <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath ſo earneſtly and obligingly both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted from all <hi>Diviſions</hi> and <hi>Diſſentions,</hi> and exhorted all to <hi>Unity</hi> and <hi>Unanimity:</hi> And ſince ſuch terrible <hi>Judgment</hi> is denounced both againſt ſuch as cauſe <hi>Scandal</hi> and <hi>Offences,</hi> and againſt ſuch as reſiſt the <hi>Ordinance of God</hi> in the Powers that be (in Church or State:) It is not to be queſtioned but this <hi>Great Schiſm,</hi> which after many <hi>Complaints</hi> of Pious and Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Perſons, and divers <hi>Warnings</hi> by the poor <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> by <hi>Wicliff,</hi> by <hi>John Huſs,</hi> and <hi>Hierome of Prague,</hi> was at last begun by <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> about <hi>180</hi> Years ſince, and is continued with much <hi>Unchriſtian Hatred and Abhorrence</hi> of one another to this day, in the principal part of his Church, is greatly <hi>diſpleaſing to our Saviour,</hi> who hath done and ſuffered ſo much for it; and very <hi>pernicious to his Church;</hi> and upon both Conſiderations juſt <hi>matter of Grief and Trouble</hi> to all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, conſiderate Chriſtians, and ſuch as is not only an effectual <hi>Motive,</hi> but a ſtrict <hi>Obligation</hi> to avoid all Participation in either the <hi>Scandals</hi> of the one ſide, or other <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> on the other, or the <hi>Animoſities</hi> between both, and to be ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute what may be toward a good <hi>Accommodation,</hi> upon true Chriſtian and Catholick Terms.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100585:3"/>
            <p>This is certainly the <hi>Duty</hi> of all; but few are ſenſible of it: The greateſt part are ſo affected to the <hi>peculiar Principles</hi> of their own Party, that they are more concerned for them and their particular Interest, than for the Common Intereſt of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity: Some in <hi>Simplicity,</hi> in fact ſuppoſing, if not expreſsly aſſerting, an Infallibility in their own Party; and others no leſs byaſſed by <hi>temporal Intereſt:</hi> and amongst thoſe of moſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and Candor, rarely any ſo clear and free from all <hi>Secret Partiality,</hi> but they are apt to vindicate their own Party in matters in difference beyond due regard to ſo deſirable an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, and deceive themſelves with Pretences of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, Peace and Charity in ſo doing, tho' thereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey make themſelves more ſpecially acceſſory to the continuance of the Schiſm, which is contrary to both, Peace and Charity, without which their pretended Obedience may be only a ſinful Compliance.</p>
            <p>Of all this I have been long ſenſible: and therefore, tho' in the Church, to which I thought my ſelf firſt and principally obliged, I ſaw divers things amiſs; yet I thought them not ſufficient to juſtifie my Separation from it: and beſides, I ſaw ſo much every where elſe amiſs, that I knew not whither to go for the better. I was for <hi>Univerſal Charity</hi> to all Men, <hi>Catholick Communion</hi> with all Chriſtians, unleſs where I ſaw ſpecial Cauſe for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and for <hi>Perfect Obedience</hi> to all Superiors according to their Authority, and conſiſtent with Duties of Prior and Superior Obligation. And then while I lived in a <hi>Civil State</hi> I acted in all things with good Satisfaction: But when I was, beyond my Expectation, ſuddenly engaged in <hi>Holy Orders,</hi> for a ſpecial Service, unto which I had been long much affected and devoted, and was then led by a ſecret ſurprizing Conduct of Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, I ſoon diſcovered what I had not ſufficiently conſidered before, in the moſt Solemn and Peculiar part of the Chriſtian Worſhip of God, which I was to perform, ſuch a Departure from the <hi>Practice of the Holy Catholick Church,</hi> that I could not perform the Obedience I would to this Particular Church, without Diſreſpect to that, and Participation therein with notorious
<pb facs="tcp:100585:3"/>Sectaries and Schiſmaticks, who had ſhamefully abuſed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon this. For this Sore I had prepared an effectual Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to have healed it, without expoſing the Shame, might it have been applied: But when I ſaw nothing could prevail, I thought it time to withdraw; and when I could not help others, to look to my ſelf; and more particularly, that I live not in <hi>Schiſm</hi> while I ſeek to avoid it: For which purpoſe I could think of no better <hi>Expedient</hi> for my Security, than, according to Ancient Practice, to ſend a Profeſſion of my Faith to ſuch Perſons as I thought moſt proper both at Home and Abroad.</p>
            <p>In <hi>the Church of Rome,</hi> and all the Churches in Communion with it, I acknowledge a <hi>true Apoſtolical Authority:</hi> and ſo far I do heartily imbrace it, and ſubmit to it. If they abuſe it, they muſt anſwer for it, not I: I muſt pity them, deplore the Abuſes, pray for them, and, as a dutiful Child, do what I can for them without partaking in or incouraging any thing amiſs. But in <hi>thoſe who pretend to be Reformed,</hi> and particularly here in <hi>England,</hi> I can diſcover no ſuch Authority neither in the Root, nor in the Fruit: but they ſeem to me like Branches ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Body, deprived of the true Sap, and nouriſhed only by the common Air, and a peculiar Juice of another kind, according to the different Soils they are planted in. Yet do I not think fit to remit any thing of my Charity and Good Will to any of them, or readineſs to ſerve them. Nor do I know how better to expreſs it than by ſuch plain dealing as I have here uſed. It is but the effect of that Fidelity which I owe to God, and to his Church, and to themſelves alſo. Even in that very Reſpect with which I treat the Authority of Christ in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> tho' it may appear to them like Partiality at the firſt, I do intend a Kindneſs to them in an exemplary Admonition, to diſtinguiſh between the Authority of Christ committed to Man, and the Faults of Men intruſted with it; and not to deſire the Deſtruction of the Field of our Lord becauſe the Enemy hath ſowed Tares in it. And that they may perceive, if they obſerve and conſider well, what Care I take not to betray any Truth of God, which I believe
<pb facs="tcp:100585:4"/>to be ſuch, by any falſe Colours, or unfit Compliance. For I have not written any thing but what I believe to be true; yet if I be miſtaken in any thing ſhall be glad to be better inform'd: and tho' I think I cannot better approve my Reſpect to our Saviour, than by much Concern for his Church; yet I think I cannot better demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the Sincerity of my Affection to it, than by not complying with ſuch things as, I fear, will provoke farther Diſpleaſure of our Lord againſt it, if the Warnings and Admonitions of more gentle Corrections be not anſwered as they ought, with a due Humiliation, giving Glory to God, and Amendment. For as whole Societies of Men are apt to fall into as great Sins as particular Perſons, and ſuch as provoke as great Judgments, tho' longer before they come to the height; ſo ought the like Means of Humiliation, Self-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, giving Glory to God, and Amendment, be uſed by them to prevent greater Severities of his Judgments.</p>
            <p>If <hi>the true State and Dignity of that Church,</hi> amongst all the Churches, according to the Ordinance of God, was better conſidered on all ſides, it would ſoon make all more ſenſible of their Duties, and of their Tranſgreſſions of it, for which they have much to anſwer. For as that Church is the Principal in the Kingdom of Christ upon Earth, and hath always been ſo eſteemed, ſo ought all true and conſiderate Chriſtians to have a ſpecial concern for ſo eminent a part of the Body of Christ, and to pray for and ſeek the Peace and Proſperity of this our <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> even to the last, after the great Example of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. And, on the other ſide, they who hold ſo eminent a place in the Kingdom of Chriſt, ought not, like Men of the World, to think too highly of themſelves for the Dignity of the Place, but, like true Chriſtians, be humbled in themſelves through a due ſenſe of the Importance of the Duty, and a proportionable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for the faithful Diſcharge of it, according to the ſpecial Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one of their Founders to themſelves, <hi>Rom. 11.18, 20, 21, 22.</hi> and the neceſsary Admonition of the other, <hi>1 Pet. 5.2, 3, 4.</hi> as he himſelf had been admoniſhed by his Maſter, <hi>Jo. 21.15, 16, 17.</hi> and according to the moſt excellent Inſtructions, Directions, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions
<pb facs="tcp:100585:4"/>and Example of that great and moſt excellent Maſter of all to all; who treated all with all the Mildneſs, Gentleneſs, Condeſcention, and Tenderneſs that could be, inſtructing and ſpeaking unto them as they were able to hear it, <hi>Mark 4.33.</hi> and forbearing many things till his Diſciples could bear them, <hi>Jo. 16.12.</hi> and forbad the forbidding of ſuch as of good Will promoted his Service, and were not againſt them, tho' not yet in their Company, <hi>Mar. 9.38, 39, 40.</hi> and of ſuch as brought but little Children unto him, <hi>Mar. 10.14.</hi> and was amongst his own, not as a Lord, but as one that ſerveth, <hi>Luk. 22.24,—27.</hi> But all ought to conſider well <hi>the Nature of this Kingdom,</hi> and what is <hi>the true Intereſt</hi> of it: that it is a Spiritual Kingdom, not imaginary, but real, and moſt powerful; and to know whence, and how, that Power is to be attained, and how to be retained and uſed: and to conſider well and underſtand not only the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rules and Inſtructions given at firſt by our Lord, but the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Notices of his Pleaſure ſignified in the ſeveral Acts of his Providential Diſcipline; and what all this doth require of them in their reſpective Stations, and wiſely apply themſelves to the Performance of it. This would ſoon detect and rectifie all that is amiſs. But it is not for me, nor for this place to proceed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in diſcourſe of theſe things.</p>
            <p>Some are offended, or think it ſtrange, that I ſhould offer to communicate with the <hi>Church of France,</hi> where ſuch terrible <hi>Perſecutions</hi> are executed againſt Proteſtants. I confeſs, I pity them as Sufferers, and more as Sufferers for Conſcience, tho' per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps miſtaken Conſcience in many things; but I do not think ever the better of them for being <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> Nor do I know that the Church of <hi>France</hi> is concerned in it; but believe it proceeds from Reaſons of State; and very good reaſon I am well ſatisfied there is, that the King ſhould deſire, and uſe all juſt and reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able means, that his Subjects may all agree in the ſame Religion: The Diſturbances in that Kingdom heretofore, by bringing in Foreigners, and the Indignities that have been done by ſome of the principal of their Miniſters, with the Approbation and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe
<pb facs="tcp:100585:5"/>of too many others, to the Primitive Chriſtians, and the Catholick Church, and in them to Chriſtianity it ſelf, are things which I think deſerve a ſharp Penance. But I wiſh on each ſide it was well conſidered what is neceſſary to make their own Cauſe good in the ſight of God and Man: for I am ſure then there would ſoon be an end of their Differences. The <hi>People</hi> ought to conſider, that divers points heretofore as confidently aſserted by their Leaders as any, have ſince been detected by learned Men amongst themſelves to have been much miſtaken: and that may reaſonably make them leſs to preſume upon any of the rest: and becauſe Obedience to Civil Magiſtrates <hi>in omnib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, licitis &amp; honeſtis</hi> is a certain Duty; they ought to go as far in Obedience as they can, without any Exception, but ſuch as they can aſsure themſelves will be allowed by Almighty God, and, if it may be, by all moderate and judicious Chriſtians. Such a Tender as this I ſhould hope might move <hi>the King</hi>'s <hi>Clemency</hi> to conſider of his <hi>Terms of Conformity,</hi> that there may be nothing in them but what is truly Catholick, as to Matters of Religion, and ſuch as he can aſsuredly expect the Approbation of God, and his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in his Proceedings upon them; and to remove all Scandals out of the way; which I think as Glorious a Work as any thing he can undertake. For thoſe unhappy Diviſions are undoubtedly a Judgment of God; and Scandals a ſpecial Cauſe of it.</p>
            <p>Of how great Concern it is to this Nation that theſe matters of Religion be taken into better Conſideration I have lately al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in the <hi>Preface</hi> to my Diſcourſe <hi>Of Prayers for the Dead,</hi> ſaid as much as I thought neceſsary; and therefore forbear to ſay any more of it here.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100585:5"/>
            <head>A Profeſſion of Faith, Comprizing the <hi>Ancient Forms</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> With other Articles relating to The Terms of Communion With the preſent CHURCH OF ROME.</head>
            <byline>By <hi>E. S.</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholick.</byline>
            <p>I <hi>Believe</hi> in One <hi>GOD,</hi> the Father Almighty, Creatour of Heaven and Earth, and of all things Viſible and Inviſible:</p>
            <p>And in One <hi>LORD, Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the only begotten Son of God, begotten of his Father before all Worlds, God of God, Light of Light, very God of very God, begotten, not made, conſubſtantial with the Father, by whom all things were made; who for us Men, and for our Salvation, deſcended from Heaven, and was conceived and incarnate by the Holy Ghoſt, born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and made Man, and alſo ſuffered for us under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> was crucified, dead, and buried, deſcended into
<note n="*" place="margin">Tho we have no word of an ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with this, yet muſt this here ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie more than Dead; for that's a tautology, not fit for a Summary.</note> 
               <hi>Hades,</hi> and the third day roſe again from the Dead, according to the Scriptures; and <hi>having forty days frequently converſed with his Apoſtles, ſpeaking of the things pertaining to the Kingdom of God, [the Church] and given them Commands, [ſpecial ſecret Inſtructions]</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100585:6"/>aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth on the right Hand of God the Father Almighty; and from thence ſhall come again with Glory to judge both the Living and the Dead: Whoſe Kingdom ſhall have no End.</p>
            <p>And in the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> the Lord and Giver of Life, who proceedeth from the Father and the Son; who with the Father and the Son is together Worſhipped and Glorified; who ſpake by the Prophets.</p>
            <p>And I believe One Holy <hi>Catholick</hi> and Apoſtolick <hi>Church;</hi> the <hi>Communion of Saints;</hi> One <hi>Baptiſm</hi> for Remiſſion of Sins; <hi>and Remiſſion of Sins after Baptiſm by the Diſcipline of the Church duly executed;</hi> the Reſurrection of the Dead, and Life Everlaſting in the World to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreover,</hi> I believe, That the Article of the Belief of the <hi>Holy Catholick Church</hi> was put into the Ancient Creeds, and placed immediately after thoſe of the Holy Trinity, for ſpecial Reaſons, and as a Matter of the next greateſt
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Note.</hi> It is <hi>the Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in this World, tho' not of this World; a great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour deign'd to Mankind; a great Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and Charity: for all Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks are Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiniers and Rebels: and all in a State of Schiſm, in a State of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: and the Sin of Schiſm in the Church is a greater Sin than the Sin of Rebellion in a Civil State, tho' both may much vary according to ſeveral Circumſtances.</note> Importance to be believed, confeſſed and obſerved in Order to the reſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That this <hi>Holy Catholick Church</hi> is a <hi>Sacred Society,</hi> formed into One Body, by the Miniſtery of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, according to a <hi>General Commiſſion</hi> and <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Inſtructions</hi> received from Him, under the <hi>Conduct of his Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Special Providence,</hi> who <hi>promiſed</hi> to be with them alway, even to the end of the World; that is, with them, and their <hi>Succeſſours</hi> regularly Succeeding in their Seats, the Churches founded by them, and others conſtituted by their Succeſſours; and that the Gates of Hell ſhould never prevail againſt it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Form and Government</hi> of this Great Body, the Holy Catholick Church, by <hi>Presbyters, Biſhops, Arch-Biſhops, or Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politans, Primates, and Patriarchs,</hi> was not any <hi>Humane Project or Invention,</hi> or <hi>Caſual thing,</hi> but what was deſigned by the Wiſdom of God, as neceſſary for the <hi>Conſtitution, Preſervation, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of it, in and as One Intire Body; and was ſo formed by the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors, by the Special Inſtructions and Directions of our Saviour, and under the Conduct of the Spirit and Special Providence of God, who had prepared the <hi>Roman
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100585:6"/>Empire</hi> for a kind of <hi>Mould</hi> to form it in; and wherein it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived its compleat Formation by degrees, in a very Natural manner.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That there was ſome
<note n="*" place="margin">This is granted by Dr. <hi>Barrow</hi> upon Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, divers Reaſons, and Authority of Fathers, who generally ſeem to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance it. <hi>Tr. of Supr. Lond.</hi> 1680. <hi>p.</hi> 46, 48.</note> 
               <hi>Special Privilege,</hi> at leaſt of a <hi>Primacy,</hi> partly given to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and which he held under our Saviour, among the reſt of the Apoſtles in our Saviour's Life-time; and partly deſigned for him afterwards; as is very obſervable in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Inſtances in the Hiſtories of the Goſpel, and in divers Speeches and Actions, many of them Myſtical, of our Saviour; and was commonly believed by the Ancient Chriſtians: And that the like Priviledge, as that which he held among the Apoſtles, was by the Deſign and Order of Almighty God to <hi>continue in his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors</hi> in the <hi>Church
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Note.</hi> Thoſe glorious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Church of Chriſt, <hi>viz. Converſion of Nations,</hi> and <hi>Subjection of Secular Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> have in no part of the Catholic Church been ſo eminently and even li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as in the particular Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note> of Rome,</hi> among the reſt of the Biſhops; that Place being ordered by the Divine Wiſdom, as moſt fit for the <hi>Chief Seat</hi> in our Saviour's Kingdom, the Church, which had been occupied by the Enemy as the chief Seat in the Empire, who was then to be caſt out, and <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> to be taken for our Saviour by his two chief Apoſtles, as his Deputies: And that ſuch <hi>Privilege of the chief Seat</hi> hath been acknowledged by the Ancient Chriſtians, and in all after-Ages; and was never denied or queſtioned, but upon Claim or Uſurpation of more than due.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That this Sacred Society, being of <hi>Special Divine Inſtitution,</hi> the Government thereof is much more <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> than any Civil Authority in the World whatever: and <hi>Diſobedience</hi> thereunto a greater Sin: and the <hi>Coercive Power</hi> of the Church by <hi>Excommunication</hi> duly exerciſed a greater <hi>Puniſhment</hi> than any the Civil Authority can inflict.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That tho' both, the <hi>Sacred</hi> and the <hi>Civil</hi> Power, be the Ordinance of God; yet the Sacred is <hi>the more Excellent,</hi> in reſpect of the Author of its Conſtitution and Specification; of its more immediate relation to Him, who is the Supream Being; of its End; of the Subject being a Sacred Society; and of the Amplitude of the Society, being Catholick, diffuſed over all the World; and in reſpect of the Extent of its Coercive Power, to exclude out of the Kingdom of Chriſt, and from the Privileges thereof: And that all civil Authority ought to be Subject and Subſervient to it, <hi>both</hi> being very <hi>conſiſtent,</hi> and each having Means proper and ſufficient to maintain its own Rights: but they both ought to be <hi>mutually aſſiſtent</hi> to the Service of the Supream Lord of all, and to each other in order thereunto.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100585:7"/>
            <p n="7">7. That <hi>if any Civil Authority</hi> preſume to <hi>oppreſs</hi> any part of this Sacred Society by Perſecution, Uſurpation, or any Reſtraint or Impediment of the Free Exerciſe of the Right or Authority belonging to it, or Duty incumbent upon it; all ſuch Preſumption is Sacrilege and Impiety againſt God, and juſt Cauſe for any other civil Authority to ingage for the Relief of it: And upon Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to the Metropolitan, Primate, or Patriarch, as Occaſion may be, He, with a competent Number of others, upon
<note n="*" place="margin">What Qu. <hi>Eliz.</hi> did by Advice of her Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil in aſſiſting the <hi>Scotch, French,</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their reſpective Soveraigns, may much more be done by any others upon ſo So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn, Sacred Conſultation and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by open War on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Oppreſſed.</note> Conſultation in Synod, or by Letters, may proceed to Sentence againſt the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and that juſtly and ſolemnly declared, and ſignified to other Metropolitants and Biſhops, they may either leave it ſo to the Judgment of Almighty God, or admoniſh other civil Authorities of it, as may be judged moſt proper or neceſſary, according to the Circumſtances of the Caſe.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That becauſe nothing is more deſtructive to certain Right than Miſuſe,
<note n="†" place="margin">Such is that Doctrine, which Dr. <hi>Barrow</hi> ſaith he conteſts againſt, <hi>p.</hi> 30. §. 13, 14. But in the next §. he ſaith there are great ſtore of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the <hi>Roman</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, who contract that Power into a narrower compaſs: So that tho' he ſtrains as much as he can, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is <hi>deceived</hi> who thinks he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth all <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy</hi> in the Pope.</note> Claim of more than is due, or by a wrong Title, and falſe or inſufficient Proofs, poſſibly ill Uſe and ill Defence may have ſo obſcured <hi>the Luſtre of this Right</hi> in the Church, that Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Error may be ſome Excuſe for divers <hi>actual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations of the Civil Authority,</hi> yet is all ſuch Uſurpation in it ſelf more or leſs Sacrilegious and Impious, and what may provoke ſome <hi>Secret Curſe</hi> upon the Guilty, tho' through Ignorance or Error, eſpecially if continued after Notice: And for the Clergy to comply with it, is to betray the Rights of the Church, and of Chriſt himſelf: But for any one to aſſert and maintain any ſuch, as Lawful, or the Right of the Magiſtrate, Hereſie, and a Betraying both of Church and State; the one to Oppreſſion, the other into Sin, and Divine Vengeance the Puniſhment thereof.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That the Chriſtian Religion was inſtituted, and the <hi>Word of God</hi> taught and delivered to the World by our Saviour, and by his Apoſtles by his expreſs Command, by Preaching and Teaching <hi>viva voce,</hi> and Orders ſettled in the Church by the Apoſtles by Word and Deed, and continued by Obſervation in Fact without Writing: And whatever hath equal Evidence of Apoſtolical Authority is of Equal Authority, whether Written, as the Holy Scriptures; or Unwritten; the Writing adding nothing of Authority, but only of Evidence; as St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf exhorting the <hi>Theſſalonians to ſtand faſt, and hold the Traditions which ye have learned, whether by Word, or by our Epiſtle,</hi> makes no difference, unleſs it be in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the Word before the Epiſtle: And therefore ſince the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100585:7"/>of God hath provided <hi>a double Evidence</hi> of things concerning the Chriſtian Religion, it is not true Piety, but Impiety,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Faith,</hi> which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tend for, is that which was once <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered</hi> to the Saints, <hi>Jud.</hi> 3 whether by Word, or Writing. <hi>v.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2, 23: 15.3. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.</note> to reject either, or ſet them one againſt the other, and the common Practice of all Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, even from the Apoſtles times, as appears by <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> and in all after-Ages, to oppoſe the one, and then pervert the other to their own purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That in Matters of common Faith and Manners, and neceſſary Orders and Obſervances, wherein the Churches, founded by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Apoſtles, were by them ordinarily inſtructed and ordered <hi>viva voce,</hi> and not by Inſtructions and Orders in Writing, it is unreaſonable to interpret the Scriptures contrary to the Senſe and Practice of the Catholick Church, and the approved Rule of <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſius Lirinenſis:</hi> And in ſuch extraordinary Matters as were not commonl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taught or ordered by the Apoſtles, after the common Faith, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.4. or Matters of leſſer moment, to raiſe or maintain any Contention in the Church, eſpecially againſt the Authority, is immodeſt, uncharitable and unchriſtian,
<note place="margin">The moſt queſtioned is <hi>Matrimony,</hi> which being of ſo much Importance to Mankind, inſtituted by God, celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Solemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Church with Impoſition of Hands and Benediction of the Prieſt, often by St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſaly call'd a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> might rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed that Title; at leaſt by thoſe who contend ſo much for Enjoyments of it.</note> contrary to the Cuſtom of the Apoſtles, and of the Churches of God. <hi>v.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That tho' there be no Catholick Tradition, for any Difinite <hi>Number of Sacraments;</hi> yet ſince by <hi>the Latin Churches</hi> it has been declared that there are <hi>Seven,</hi> which are properly ſo called, and it cannot be denied that they are all Means uſed with <hi>viſible Signs,</hi> or <hi>Significant Actions,</hi> by Divine Authority, to confer or obtain ſome ſpecial Grace; it is great Inſolence, Uncharitableneſs, and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency unbecoming the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, to raiſe or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Contention againſt ſuch Authority about the Number, which may be differently computed to be either more or fewer, by reaſon that <hi>Impoſition of Hands</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> two very conſiderable Signs, and of Divine Inſtitution, may be, and are uſed for divers pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes: But becauſe there is no Evidence either of Holy Scripture, or of Catholick Tradition, that they were all particularly inſtituted by our Saviour, I cannot believe that I could with a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſafely, either ſwear or profeſs that they were, or that ſuch an Article can be made one of the Terms of Communion with any Church, without expoſing the Authority of that Church, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing the Increaſe of the Kingdom of Chriſt, and adminiſtring Occaſion of Diſſentions among his Subjects, and incurring his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, by an Act ſo unfuitable to his Example and Directions.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That it is great Preſumption and Impiety to reject or cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the received and approved <hi>Ceremonies of the Catholick Church</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100585:8"/>uſed in the Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, tho' they may not be generally underſtood: For as <hi>Origen</hi> rightly obſerves, <hi>In the Obſervations of the Church there are ſome of ſuch ſort, that it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that all obſerve them, tho' the Reaſon of them be not apparent to all:</hi> And God injoined the Obſervation of ſuch Ceremonies even to <hi>Moſes</hi> in doing of Miracles, as few know the Reaſon of, to this Day: and yet had he not obſerved them, undoubtedly the Effect had not followed. Alſo that ordinarily all Rites, Ceremonies, Obſervations and Conſtitutions, not only of the Catholick Church, but of National, Provincial, and particular Dioceſian Churches, not diſallowed by ſuperior Authority, ought reverently and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly to be obſerved, till they be regularly altered. But ſpecial Care ought to be taken that the <hi>Divine Inſtitutions,</hi> which only are Eſſential and abſolutely neceſſary, be not confounded eclipſed, or obſcured by <hi>Multiplicity</hi> or <hi>Formality</hi> of any <hi>Additions of Humane Invention:</hi> tho' it be very probable that in the Inſtitution of them in ſo great <hi>Simplicity,</hi> and the Records of them with ſo much <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,</hi> there might be a <hi>Divine Deſign</hi> to leave Circumſtantials and Matters of Indifference to the Ordering of the Church, both to expreſs her Devotion, and to exerciſe her Authority, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Humility, Submiſſion, and Obedience, Graces very neceſſary to qualifie Souls for the Coeleſtial State, and not ſo naturally improved as by Exerciſe under Creatures of the ſame Rank and Order.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That the Word <hi>Miſſa,</hi> (in <hi>Engliſh, The Maſs</hi>) was in the <hi>Latin</hi> Churches in the times of St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> and St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and before commonly uſed for what in the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches was called <hi>Liturgia:</hi> that <hi>the Canon of the Maſs,</hi> which is the principal part, is the <hi>moſt Ancient Form</hi> for the Celebration of <hi>the Holy Euchariſt,</hi> that is known to have been uſed in any of the <hi>Latin</hi> Churches, more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient than the times aforeſaid, and in common uſe in all or in moſt of the <hi>Latin</hi> Churches, without any conſiderable Variations in all Ages ſince, tho' there were divers Variations in other parts: And that in the due Celebration of the <hi>Bleſſed Eucharist</hi> there is not only a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> but alſo a
<note n="*" place="margin">In this have with me, beſides the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Church in all Ages, which Mr. <hi>Joſ. Mede</hi> hath ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to my hand, the concurrent Judgment of the moſt learned <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Clergy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince the firſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy was compoſed.</note> 
               <hi>Sacrifice</hi> commemorative of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Paſſion and Sacrifice of Himſelf upon the Croſs, as <hi>effectual</hi> to all Intents and Purpoſes for Chriſtians, as were any or all the Sacrifices of the <hi>Jews</hi> for them: that therein is performed <hi>the moſt Solemn and Peculiar part of the true Chriſtian Worſhip:</hi> that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly it hath been held in great Veneration, and much frequented with great Reverence and Devotion by a great Number of Saints,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100585:8"/>and all the moſt Holy Chriſtians in all Ages: that <hi>the Oppoſition,</hi> which hath been raiſed againſt both Name and Thing, hath been raiſed through the Malice and by the ſubtile Energy or Operation of the Devil: and that to deny the ſame is Hereſie; and to aboliſh out of the Publick Liturgy of any Church what doth import any thing of an unbloody Sacrifice, Sacrilege, and Anti-Chriſtian Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety. <hi>v. Dan.</hi> 8.31.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That the <hi>Commemoration of the Saints</hi> in the moſt Solemn Chriſtian Worſhip is a common Practice of the whole Catholick Church, of great Antiquity and immemorial Preſcription, without any known Beginning, of very commendable Obſervation for the <hi>Communion of Saints,</hi> which we profeſs to believe; an Act of Charity, Honour, and Reſpect to them, well-pleaſing to God, and beneficial <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> our ſelves, in rendring Thanks to God for them, with Prayers for our ſelves that we may follow their Example, and have Communion, Part and Society with them, and a part in the Benefit of their Prayers: and that to put that out of the Service ſavours of a Complication of very evil Humours; as Superſtition, Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, Contempt of the Authority of the Catholick Church, Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of Reformation, Contention, and malicious Reflection of <hi>Odium</hi> upon others, and Separation from the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, of which they were moſt illuſtrious Members, through the Deluſion and Inſtigation of the wicked Anti-Chriſtian Spirit, who being overcome by them, through Chriſt dwelling in them, abhor all Acts of Affection and Reſpect to them, and that their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs ſhould be celebrated to the Honour of Chriſt, who is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured in them, and for whoſe Sake all is performed to them.</p>
            <p n="15">15.
<note place="margin">Of this I have lately print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> dedicated to the Lord Chancellour and Judges.</note> That <hi>Prayers for the Dead</hi> departed in the Communion of the Church in this Solemn Worſhip, is alſo a Practice of the whole Catholick Church, of as great Evidence of Apoſtolical Authority, as part of the Holy Scripture it ſelf, and other things believed and obſerved by thoſe who oppoſe it; Innocent, Inoffenſive, Charitable, Deſirable; oppoſed only upon the ſame Principles, Motives, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and Inſtigations, with that laſt mentioned.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That in the <hi>Holy Euchariſt</hi> there is a <hi>Divine Change</hi> of the Elements from common Bread and common Wine, by the Deſcent of the Holy Spirit at the Prayer of the Church, whereby they are conſecrated, not by a meer Separation for a Sacred uſe, but by an actual Sanctification, and made the Body and Blood of Chriſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with a Divine Power and Virtue for the Sanctification of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100585:9"/>the duly diſpoſed Communicants: But I cannot ſay <hi>a Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> becauſe I find no Catholick Tradition for that in the vulgar Senſe; but rather the contrary, as appears by that of <hi>Ireaeus, duabus rebus conſtans, coeleſti &amp; terrena,</hi> and the like in <hi>Theodoret</hi> and others; nor doth it ſeem neceſſary, or neceſſarily implyed in any words of our Saviour recorded in the Goſpel; tho' <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Nyſſen,</hi> and ſome others may ſeem to favour it: But if there be any proper Explication of it to a Senſe truly Catholick, I conceive it becomes not any private Perſon to contend with Authority about a Word; only the vulgar ſenſe of Tranſubſtantiation I cannot ſubſcribe to, and doubt it is Scandalous, and prejudicial to the Intereſt of the Kingdom of Chriſt, eſpecially to make it <hi>a Term of Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. That for <hi>Communion in one kind in publick Aſſemblies,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial of the Cup to the Laity,</hi> there is no Appearance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Authority, but the quite contrary for above 1000 years, even in the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, and in all other Churches to this Day: Nor was it introduced at firſt upon any good Deliberation and Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Clergy, but as evil Cuſtoms, and Abuſes crep in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly: That for any part of the Church to preſume to impoſe it upon all National and Provincial Churches, who have Authority to order ſuch things as are lawful in themſelves, as they ſee moſt expedient for their own People, ſeems to ſavour of great Arrogance, unjuſt Uſurpation, and an Occaſion of Diſturbance in the Peaceful Kingdom of Chriſt. Men of Wit and Parts may ſay much for any thing: But in ſuch matters it is good to conſider whom we have to do with, leſt we betray our own Souls, and the Church too, which we pretend to ſerve, by our Unfaithfulneſs to it, as well as to our Lord, to ſome Divine Judgment. It is fit the Church it ſelf ſhould give Example to all, if there be Occaſion, of Humiliation and giving Glory to God. I can ſubmit, for Peace ſake, and out of reſpect to Authority, to what I cannot approve: but that will aggravate the Sin of thoſe who abuſe the Authority committed to them.</p>
            <p n="18">18. That the Cuſtom of <hi>attending at Maſs without Communicating,</hi> is not of any truly Catholick Uſage or Authority, but contrary to the moſt ancient Canons of the Church; to the common Practice of the firſt Ages, and to the earneſt Exhortations of moſt Eminent Perſons,
<note n="*" place="margin">It is very remarkable that the <hi>great Confuſions</hi> in the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches, and <hi>Decays of true Piety</hi> in the <hi>Latin,</hi> ſoon iſſued after their <hi>Neglect of frequent Communion</hi> began, as if by a ſpecial and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. To be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently one ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> both of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches; proceeded from Decays of Devotion at firſt, and hath produced greater; ſeems to ſavour of Diſreſpect to our Saviour, and to be very prejudicial to his People; being an implicit refuſal of Communion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100585:9"/>of the Holy Covenant with him, which is implicitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the Act of Communion; and an inconſiderate and ingrateful Neglect of a moſt Holy and effectual Means of Grace, moſt graciouſly offered to them: ſo that as by what was laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned they are deprived of part, by this they are defrauded of the whole: And in both the Subtilty of the Serpent is much to be ſuſpected.</p>
            <p n="19">19.
<note place="margin">Nothing ſeems more likely to have provoked ſo ſevere a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God upon this Church by <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. than the Severities before-exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed upon People for what was commended in and by the ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Teaching the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage they underſtood.</note> That to keep the Publick Offices of the Church and the Holy Scriptures in a <hi>Language not underſtood by the People,</hi> hath no Apoſtolical or true Catholick Authority, but is directly contrary to both; was at firſt the Effect of that Alteration of Languages which Wars and other Occurrences produced, not only in the <hi>Latin,</hi> but <hi>Greek</hi> Churches alſo; and is ſtill ſo continued in both, and others beſides: which, were it through Negligence, ſeems hardly excuſable; much leſs juſtifiable, where by Prohibition or Injunction; but rather ſcandalous, as if deſigned to conceal an ill Cauſe; however ſeems to ſavour more of Worldly and Humane Wiſdom, than of the true Chriſtian and Divine; to be a great Occaſion of Diſſentions, a great Obſtacle of Re-union, and Diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the Kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="20">20. That <hi>Prayers to Saints</hi> departed hath no Apoſtolick or true Catholick Authority or Warrant, according to the approved Rule before-mentioned; yet if there be nothing equivalent againſt it, ſince it hath
<note n="*" place="margin">Near 1300 Years.</note> long ſince been a received Practice of the whole Catholick Church in all Parts of the World, and of many Perſons greatly honoured by God with extraordinary Graces, Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, and very great Bleſſings and Succeſs in his Service; and ſince ſpecial Honor to the Memories of Martyrs hath the Authority of a true Catholick Practice, and of Divine Approbation by Miracles, atteſted by moſt credible and eminent Perſons in the Church, ſuch as S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſtom, &amp;c.</hi> it ſeems great Preſumption to cenſure it, as many do. But it is very likely that divers and great <hi>Abuſes</hi> may have been, and are committed in the Practice, which, by the Permiſſion of God, hath raiſed ſuch a Storm of Reformation, through the Malice of the Devil againſt it: Which Abuſes, if they be not already, ought carefully to be reformed and repreſſed: and eſpecially in the Uſe of <hi>Pictures and Images,</hi> by reaſon of the Scandal and Offence by them given both to <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Mahometans,</hi> and to many Chriſtians; whereof an Account will undoubtedly be required. <hi>v. Lu.</hi> 17.1, 2.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100585:10"/>
            <p n="21">21. That the Uſe of the <hi>Sign of the Croſs</hi> hath that Authority from the known Practice of the Ancient Chriſtians, and that Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Divine Approbation in the Converſion and Victories of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> that tho' it is probable that the Abuſes of it, which have been committed and permitted in the Church, may have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked the Diſpleaſure of God; yet the furio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Oppoſition and Indignation which hath been ſhewed againſt it, looks very like the Effect of the Malice and Revenge of the Powers of Darkneſs let looſe, which had been ſo affronted, terrified and expoſed by it, inſtigating a contrary Superſtition and abuſed Zeal in the People. Which therefore requires that ſpecial Care be taken, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity be not expoſed, and the poor People abuſed into falſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidences, by things, which, tho' innocent and uſeful in themſelves, may notwithſtanding be ſubject to much Abuſe.</p>
            <p n="22">22. That <hi>the Diſcipline</hi> of the Church is a Matter of very great Importance for the Maintenance and Preſervation of the Honour and Power of Religion; ſo Powerful a Means, that, if exerciſed as it ought, it would ſoon make all the World to know who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; and the greateſt Kings and Emperors to ſubmit their Crowns and Scepters to his Empire: But the Imprudence and Unfaithfulneſs of his Miniſters, in deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their true and proper Strength, and applying to the Arm of Fleſh, made it neceſſary for him to withdraw his Glorious Preſence, and leave them to experiment the Inſufficiency and Deceitfulneſs of the Supports they had choſen, till at laſt finding nothing but an empty Shell, they were willing to make the beſt they could of it. Tho' it be very true, that <hi>the Power of Indulgencies</hi> was given and left by Chriſt to his Church, and the Uſe of them is very beneficial and neceſſary for his Church and People: yet was that Power, tho' promiſed firſt to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> when actually given, given alike to all the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors in all Parts of the Catholick Church: but that which ſince the Twelfth Age hath been exerciſed as a Prerogative, and is the only thing now commonly underſtood by
<note n="*" place="margin">V. <hi>Morin. de Paenitentia, lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 16, 20, 21. It is not true Humility, but Stupidity, &amp; Unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to God and his Church, not to be moved at ſo great an Indignity to God, Abuſe of his People, Scandal to Religion, and Danger of greater Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon themſelves, by ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable a part of his Church; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if after all the Practice be ſtill continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> 
               <hi>Indulgencies,</hi> is a mere Abuſe of the Chriſtian Diſcipline, an Abuſe of the Credulity of the People, a Scandalous Abuſe: And to cover ſuch an Abuſe, under pretence of that Sacred Authority, and after ſuch a Judgment as it hath brought upon the Church, inſtead of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Humiliation, and Amendment, and to make the Belief of it one of the Terms of Communion too, is another complicated Abuſe too groſs to be impoſed upon any Mortal of competent Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100585:10"/>and too bold a Preſumption to be unconcernedly born by any one of an unprejudiced Chriſtian Spirit; or to be Believ'd will eſcape a more ſevere Judgment of God, if not timely prevented by a requiſite Humiliation, and ſuch a Reſtitution of the true Chriſtian Diſcipline as may in ſome ſort countervail the Miſchief of that Abuſe.</p>
            <p n="23">23. That Souls not perfectly purified in this Life do after Death paſs through <hi>a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate of Purgation,</hi> I do believe as a probable Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; but that they may receive Benefit by the Prayers, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Good Works of the Faithful Surviving, I do believe upon good Evidence of Apoſtolical Authority, beſides other conſiderable Motives.</p>
            <p n="24">24. That tho' the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> be the Firſt or Chief Seat, and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> the Chief Paſtor in the whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, and by the Ordination of God ſo conſtituted by the two C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ef Apoſtles, as a Matter of great Importance in the Body of the Catholick Church, and ought therefore to be ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all Chriſtians;
<note place="margin">V. <hi>Bar. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 912. <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebr. l.</hi> 4. § 10. To oppoſe plain Matter of Fact with Promiſes and <hi>Predictions,</hi> in a ſtrict ſenſe, is to give Scandal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction: And to defend or palliate what is amiſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Glory to God, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending and under re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Judgments, is not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with Piety, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or Honeſty.</note> yet I cannot call or think it the <hi>Mother</hi> of all Churches, for that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> certainly was; nor the <hi>Miſtreſs</hi> neither; for I neither think that her Right, nor well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to her Lord that ſhe ſhould aſſume it: but that as it is certain, that tho' our Saviour conferred divers Favours and ſome ſpecial Privilege upon St. <hi>Peter</hi> above the reſt, and prayed ſpecially for him, when Satan deſired them to ſift them as Wheat, that his Faith might not fail; yet he did fall foully, even in his Maſter's Preſence, and again after his Aſcenſion did warp a little, and yield to the Tentation, for which he was reproved by St. <hi>Paul;</hi> ſo <hi>his Succeſſors</hi> in that Church, whatever Privileges or Promiſes they may or can pretend, have <hi>in like manner fallen</hi> (as perhaps was Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſignified in that Fall of their Founder) for ſome time very foully; partly by <hi>Claiming, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping and Exerciſing</hi> more than their due; which hath cauſed much Diſturbance in the World, and, at laſt, what is really their Right, or their Due and Duty, to be queſtioned, diſputed, and ſo made doubtful, and actually rejected in many Places; and partly by ſuch other <hi>Abuſes, Corruptions, Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, and Scandals,</hi> as overſpreading all, moved great Complaints and Diſcontents, and earneſt Defires and Prayers for an Orderly Reformation, and at laſt produced, when nothing elſe could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, by the ſpecial Providence of Almighty God, one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Schiſms, all things conſidered, that in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Church hath ever been known: and laſtly, by requiring ſuch <hi>Terms of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100585:11"/>as are not neceſſary for the Service of our Lord, but much to the Diſſervice of his Intereſt, by hindring the Re-union of many well-diſpoſed People, and contrary to his <hi>Example, Directions</hi> &amp; <hi>Will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">25. That the Conſtitution of the Church of God, and the Powers and Authorities ſettled in it, are not to be altered, or ſubject to Alteration by ſuch Ways and Means as civil Conſtitutions, Powers and Authorities uſually are; as by Forfeiture, or voluntary Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo as to effect any Diminution of the Power or Authority of its Succeſſor: And therefore the <hi>preſent Biſhop of Rome,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any Miſcarriages of any of his Predeceſſours, hath as much Power and Authority in the Catholick Church, as any ſince St. <hi>Peter</hi> (who had an Authority Superior to all Biſhops) in that Seat ever had, (unleſs there be any thing Perſonal againſt himſelf:) and in him the Power and Authority of that Seat ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, aſſerted, and maintained by all Chriſtians, as the Power and Authority of Chriſt, and for his Service and Intereſt: that to reject that is impious, Schiſmatical, and Heretical: but yet the Perſonal Miſcarriages of thoſe that are or ſhall be in that Seat, may be judged, cenſured and corrected by the Churches of the ſame Diviſion or Patriarcate, either in one general Council, or in ſeveral National and Provincial Synods, agreeing generally up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a mutual Communication of Votes in the ſame Sentence. But this is a Matter which, as it is of great Conſequence, ſo ought to be managed with great Circumſpection and much Application by all to God for his Divine Conduct.</p>
            <p n="26">26. That the Authority even of National and Provincial <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils</hi> duly aſſembled, and proceeding regularly, ought to be reſpected, and treated with Reverence by all Chriſtians; and if their Acts be received with a general Approbation of many other ſuch, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of equal Authority with a <hi>General</hi> Council of all thoſe Churches. But Acts of Councils call'd general, if not regularly and unanimouſly paſſed in Council, or not generally received and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved afterward, but diſapproved, either by expreſs Declaration, by contrary Practice, or notorious different Sentiments of the greateſt, or a very conſiderable part of the Catholick Church, are of little Obligation; yet ought not to be reproachfully or rudely oppoſed, but rather decently buried in Silence, or by a more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Determination.</p>
            <p n="27">27. That every <hi>Provincial Synod</hi> under one Metropolitan is a compleat Repreſentation or Model of the whole Catholick Church, (which conſiſts and is compacted of many ſuch Sacred Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100585:11"/>and hath a <hi>compleat Authority</hi> of it ſelf to order all matters of Religion,
<note place="margin">Againſt this Noble and <hi>Compleat Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of the Churches of Chriſt have many things been very injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and ſcandalouſly done both by Secular Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and by Popes and Patriarchs: The Sins of both, and of ſuch as have too eaſily yeilded to them, are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great, and will undoubt edly be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, as of Rebels and Traitors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Supream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, if not prevented here.</note> and to correct and reform what is amiſs within their own Territories, according to the common Rules of the Catholick Church; ſubject notwithſtanding to the Judgment, Cenſure and Correction of more general Councils, in caſe they act any thing contrary to thoſe Rules: But in Matters, whether of Belief or Practice, not de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rmined by Catholick Evidence of Apoſtolical Authority, and which are therefore left at Liberty, it may be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to impoſe any thing: but if any thing be thought neceſſary or expedient of that Nature, it ought rather to be gently recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, than Majeſterially impoſed, leaſt Authority be unadviſedly expoſed, and Catholick Unity and Charity indangered.</p>
            <p n="28">28. That in all <hi>Differences in the Church,</hi> all Parties ought to be very careful for the Preſervation of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Charity,</hi> as Matters of the great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt Importance in the Kingdom of Chriſt; the very Difference being a fair Warning and Admonition for Godly Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie and ſpecial Caution and Circumſpection to all Parties for the Peace of the Church, the Satisfaction of the differing Party, and the Security of the Juſtice and Righteouſneſs of their own Cauſe, leſt it either be ill, or if good at firſt in it ſelf, it become ill through ill Management; and therefore to proceed peaceably, patiently, and amicably;
<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8. —13.10.</note> 
               <hi>Superiors</hi> with Gentleneſs and Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention, as having their Authority for Edification, not for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and therefore not Lording it over their Subjects; and <hi>Inferiors</hi> with Humility, Modeſty, Reſpect, and Submiſſion, that they reſiſt not the Ordinance of God; each as far as Duty and ſincere Conſcience will allow; with hearty Deſire and ſincere En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour for Accommodation, and Grief and Sorrow if it cannot be obtained, and without any abatement of Charity notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; but with Pity for the Faults of others.</p>
            <p n="29">29. That tho' there was much need of a <hi>Reformation,</hi> when the Work ſo called was begun, yet was <hi>not</hi> that Work, as it was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, <hi>any Work of God,</hi> as <hi>ordered</hi> by Him, <hi>but</hi> only as <hi>permitted</hi> by Him for a <hi>Judgment</hi> upon the Church, which would not reform, and executed by the Inſtigation of adverſe Powers; as may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in 1. the <hi>Qualities of the Perſons</hi> who were the principal Leaders and Actors in it, and 2. the <hi>Means</hi> uſed to effect it; all merely Humane, nothing truly Spiritual and Divine, (I intend not in this the Scriptures in themſelves, but the Uſe which was made of them I do) no Demonſtration of Spirit and Power; in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100585:12"/>3. the <hi>Manner,</hi> with much Arrogance, Inſolence, Malice, Hatred, Violence, Injuſtice, Oppreſſion, Sacrilege, and Profanation of Sacred things, Factions, Tumults, and hot Contentions among themſelves; all plain Indications of what Spirit they were: and, 4. in the <hi>Matter or Work effected,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hence the true Cauſe of the <hi>Contempt</hi> of the <hi>Clergy: Ye have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo have made you Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible,</hi> &amp;c. Mal. 2.7, 8, 9.</note> deſtructive of the <hi>Government,</hi> of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, of the Diſcipline, and of the Doctrine of the Catholick Church of Chriſt; all accommodated to recommend the Preachers, to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the natural Diſpoſition of the People, to raiſe Prejudice and Odium againſt the Church, and to draw away Diſciples after them; but ſecretly tending to the Diſſolution and Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Kingdom of Chriſt upon Earth, with divers ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Gratifications of thoſe adverſe Powers: and, laſtly, in 5. the <hi>Fruits and
<note n="†" place="margin">is very remarkable, That many of the moſt Learned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, both Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts and Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, are gone off from divers Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the firſt Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and confeſs the Papiſts have been falſly charged and wronged in divers things.</note> Effects,</hi> a Form of Godlineſs, but little of the Power; much Talk of Religion, but little of the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue Works; much in the Head, but little in the Heart; ſome Beginnings, ſome little Progreſs, but rarely any thing brought to Perfection, or more compleat than the Chickens which are ſaid to be hatched in ſome artificial Stoves, which, tho' otherwiſe brought to Maturity, are all maimed in one part or other; and generally <hi>Decays of Piety and Virtue,</hi> even from the beginning, ſuch as made <hi>Luther</hi> complain, That ſince the Goſpel was preached in its Purity, (as he called it) People were grown worſe than under the Papacy. And certainly, if we come to <hi>Compariſon,</hi> as to the Fruits, one Diſciple of <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> ſince <hi>Luther, Francis Xavier,</hi> a Miſſioner of the Pope, produced more true <hi>Evangelical Fruits</hi> in the compaſs of Ten Years, or little more, in Converſion of Infidels, and more <hi>illuſtrious Evidences of a Divine Power</hi> with him, than all the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers put together ever ſince <hi>Luther</hi> began to this day; which is a great Divine Atteſtation, both to his Order, and to the Authority by which he was ſent; and the more conſiderable in reſpect of the Time, the very time of the pretended Reformation, as if or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered on purpoſe by the Divine Providence for an Evidence of the Difference of the Spirits, by which the two Works were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted. And if we conſider <hi>the Effects in reſpect of the Church of Rome,</hi> I believe they will not, upon a juſt Examination, appear to have been better in thoſe who, on pretence of Reformation, have made the Separation, than in the Church they have gone out of; and that there wants nothing but a more compleat Reformation of the Churches of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion for a final Demonſtration, by an end of this <hi>pretended Reformation;</hi> that it was no other than a temporary Judgment, for Correction of what was amiſs in the Church.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100585:12"/>
            <p n="30">30. That among all the pretended Reformations it may be a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether any was introduced with greater Wickedneſs, or ſettled at laſt with greater Faults, than this <hi>of the Church of England,</hi> how much ſoever magnified by ſuch as have or expect Preferments in it. But to paſs by the <hi>wicked Practices,</hi> firſt to hector and terrifie, with falſe Accuſations and Pretences, <hi>Wolſey</hi> out of his Life; then the reſt of the Clergy into a Recognition of an Antichriſtian Supremacy, and Subjection of the Rights of the Church to the Will of a wicked Tyrant; then the Superiors of the Religious Houſes to ſurrender all their Goods and Eſtates; and then, by like Practices, to get all confirmed by Act of Parliament, partly hectoring, and partly bribing and ingaging the Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, with the Spoils, into a Compliance with the moſt horrible Sacrilege and Devaſtation of the Goods and Eſtates of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, of which ten Thouſand at a time were turned out, and put to ſhift for themſelves with <hi>Forty Shillings</hi> and a <hi>Gown</hi> a piece; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this, the Guilt of which may ſtill remain, there are theſe <hi>Monſtrous Faults</hi> the Effects of that Wickedneſs ſtill remaining in the Conſtitution of this Reformed Church:</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the <hi>Government,</hi> a Sacrilegious Uſurpation upon the Rights of the Church in the Nomination of Biſhops, Deans, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with a prophane Mockery, or Abuſe of a Mock Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Perſons impoſed upon them: and in holding Synods, and making and executing Canons and Conſtitutions, all continued in the Power of the Prince by Act of Parliament, and given up by the Clergy: So that if we have Biſhops, as they are called, they are neither Canonically choſen, nor are permitted, or dare to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe any Authority of a National Church: And ſhould we have a Deiſt, Infidel, or one ill affected to Chriſtianity, what a Church might here be expected in a few Years?</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is a mutinous Body, actually <hi>ſeparated</hi> from the great Body of the Kingdom of Chriſt, the Catholick Church; and hath no actual <hi>Communion</hi> with any Church, which is not broken off from that Body; or which is regularly and orderly by Succeſſion of Presbyters deſcended from the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As to the <hi>Worſhip,</hi> the Publick Liturgy has been ſo curtelled and diſordered by <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and a ſecret Faction, in the principal part, that they have aboliſhed not only the Commemoration of the Saints, and Prayers for the Dead, but even the Prayer at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration for the Deſcent of the Holy Spirit, and whatever might
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100585:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>import any thing of Oblation of the Commemorative Sacrifice of our Saviour's Paſſion; which hath always been reputed the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, moſt Solemn and Peculiar part of the Chriſtian Worſhip throughout the whole Catholick Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As for <hi>the Diſcipline,</hi> if we have Biſhops, they are ſo awed by the Civil Authority on the one ſide with Prohibitions, and ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered by their Chancellours on the other, that there is little left for them to exerciſe of the proper Authority of a Dioceſian Church; but they bear the blame of thoſe Scandals they cannot remedy.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But after all, it may be a Queſtion, <hi>Whether we have Biſhops;</hi> that is, true Chriſtian Biſhops at all, or only a ſort of <hi>State Biſhops,</hi> without any true Spiritual and Apoſtolical Authority, or other than what was derived from the King, and dependent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon him?</p>
            <p>Theſe things being ſo, I thought it my Duty to make this <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith,</hi> and <hi>Declaration;</hi> That I <hi>Diſclaim, Renounce and Deteſt</hi> that Horrible <hi>Sacrilege</hi> of the <hi>Diſſolution of the Monaſteries;</hi> that greater Sacrilege of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation by the Civil Authority of the Rights of the Church</hi> inſtituted by Divine Authority; the Sacrilegious <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the Liturgy;</hi> the <hi>Eraſtian</hi> Hereſie of <hi>Cranmer;</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation</hi> and Execution of the Right-Reverend Biſhop <hi>Fiſher,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas More,</hi> and the reſt, who ſuffered in Perſon; and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation and Deprivation of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> who ſuffered in their Rights and Eſtates, for Denying, Contradicting, or Refuſing to Swear to the pretended Supremacy of the Civil Power in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Matters, and all Laws, Statutes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which reſtrain the free Exerciſe of the Chriſtian Diſcipline, or any Rites of the Church, or were intended to eſtabliſh, confirm or authorize any of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, Uſurpations, Corruptions or Condemnations aforeſaid, as wicked, unjuſt, and Schiſmatical, and contrary to the Law of God, and to one of the chief Fundamental Principles of the Laws of this Land: and that I do ſincerely and heartily deſire an <hi>actual Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> as there may be occaſion, with all Churches under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of a regular Succeſſion of Biſhops and Presbyters from the Apoſtles of our Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> and in actual Communion with the Catholick Church, and deſire it particularly with the <hi>Church of France,</hi> being the next ſo qualified: and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto do hereby for my part humbly make a Publick Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereof.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
